Hello everyone, this is Father Andrew.
In 2021, at the end of our Holy Week and Pascha episode, which was titled The Lord of
Spirits Goes to Hell, I read a short excerpt from the Herald of Hell section of a text
variously referred to as the Gospel of Nicodemus or the Acts of Pilate.
This text is generally regarded as an apocryphal New Testament.
text. What does that mean? It reflects traditions surrounding events of the New Testament that are not
actually included in Scripture. So this isn't a text from the Bible and we don't treat it that way.
But one of the distinctions from the ancient church that we have mentioned many times on the
podcast is between three categories of books. Books read in church, books read at home,
and books not to be read.
The first category is Scripture, books, read, and church.
The last category, books not to be read, is heretical texts that are harmful to one's salvation.
This text, the Gospel of Nicodemus, is that second category, books to be read at home.
A number of orthodox liturgical texts make use of this text, giving it an honored place
within our tradition of worship.
After I read that excerpt, we received a lot of positive.
feedback as this was many people's first encounter with this amazing piece of writing that
seems to have taken its present form in the 4th or 5th century.
Because of that feedback, I wanted to read for you the harrowing of hell in its entirety,
as found in the Gospel of Nicodemus.
We begin with St. Joseph of Erymothea speaking to Annas and Caiaphas, two high priests of the
temple during the time of Jesus.
And Joseph arose and said unto Anna St. Caiaphas,
Truly end of right to ye marvel because ye have heard that Jesus has been seen alive after death.
death, and that he had ascended into heaven. Nevertheless, it is more marvelous that he
rose not alone from the dead, but did raise up alive many other dead out of their sepokers,
and they have been seen of many in Jerusalem. And now, harken unto me, for we all know the
blessed Simeon, the high priest which received the child Jesus in his hands in the temple.
And this Simeon had two sons, brothers in blood, and we all were at their falling asleep
and
that's their burial. Go therefor and look upon their supplekers for they are open, because
they have risen, and behold they are in the city of Arimathea dwelling together in
prayer. And indeed men hear them crying out yet they speak with no man, but are silent
as dead men. But come let us go into them, and with all honor and gentleness, bring them
unto us. And if we adjure them perchance they will tell us concerning the mystery of their
rising again.
When they heard these things, they all rejoiced.
And Anas and Caiaphas, Nicodemus and Joseph and Gamelio went and found them not in their
subduker, but they went unto the city of Eremathea, and found them there kneeling on their
knees and giving themselves unto prayer.
And they kissed them and with all reverence and in the fear of God, they brought them to
Jerusalem into the synagogue.
and they shut the doors and took the law of the Lord and put it into their hands.
and adjured them by the Lord God and the God of Israel which spake unto our
fathers by the prophet, saying,
believe ye that it is Jesus which raised you from the dead?
Tell us how ye have arisen from the dead.
And when Kareness and Levchius heard this adoration,
they trembled in their body and groaned being troubled in heart.
And looking up together unto heaven, they made the seal of the cross with their
fingers upon their tongues and forthwith, they spake both of them, saying,
Give us each
a volume of paper, and let us write that which we have seen and heard, and they gave them
unto them, and each of them sat down and wrote, saying,
O Lord Jesus Christ, the life and resurrection of the dead,
Suffer us to speak of the mysteries of thy majesty which thou disperformed after thy death
upon the cross, in as much as we have been adjured by thy name.
Without its command us thy servants to tell no man the secrets of thy divine majesty.
which thou wroughtest in hell. Now when we were set together with all our fathers in the deep,
in obscurity of darkness, on a sudden there came a golden heat of the sun and a purple and royal
light shining upon us, and immediately the father of the whole race of men, together with all the
patriarchs and prophets rejoiced, saying, this light is the beginning of everlasting light which
it promised to send unto us his co-eternal light.
Isaiah cried out and said,
This is the light of the Father, even the Son of God, according as I prophesied when I lived upon the earth.
The land of Zebulon and the land of Nethalim, beyond Jordan of Galilee of the Gentiles,
the people that walked in darkness have seen a great light,
and they that dwell in the land of the shadow of death upon them to the light shine,
and now hath it come and shown upon us that sit in death.
and as we all rejoiced in the light which shined upon us.
there came unto us our Father Simeon, and he rejoicing said unto us,
Glorify ye the Lord Jesus Christ the Son of God, for I received him in my hands in the temple
when he was born a child, and being moved of the Holy Spirit I made confession and said unto him,
Now have my eyes seen thy salvation which thou hast prepared before the face of all people,
a light to lighten the Gentiles, and to be the glory of thy people Israel.
and when they heard these things the whole multitude of the scenes.
rejoiced yet more.
And after that, there came one as it were, a dweller in the wilderness.
And he was inquired of by all, who art thou?
And he answered them and said, I am John, the voice and the prophet of the most high,
which came before the face of his advent to prepare his ways to give knowledge of salvation
and to his people for the remission of their sins.
And when I saw him coming and to me being moved to the Holy Spirit, I said, behold the
Lamb of God behold him that takeeth away the sins of the world, and I baptised him in
the river of Jordan, and saw the Holy Spirit descending upon him in the likeness of a dove,
and heard a voice out of heaven saying, This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleased.
And now have I come before his face, and come down to declare unto you that he is at hand
to visit us, even the day spring, the Son of God, coming from on high unto us that sit in
darkness and in the shadow of darkness.
death.
And when Father Adam that was first created heard this, even the Jesus was baptized in Jordan.
He cried out to Seth his son, saying,
Declare unto thy sons the patriarchs and the prophets, all that thou dost hear from
Michael the Archangel when I sensed thee unto the gates of Paradise, that thou mightest
entreat God to send thee his angel to give thee the oil of the tree of mercy to anoint
my body when I was sick.
and Seth turn near onto the holy...
patriarchs and prophets and said, When I, Seth, was praying at the gates of paradise,
behold, Michael, the angel of the Lord appeared unto me, saying, I am sent unto thee from
the Lord, it is I that am set over the body of man. And I say unto thee, Seth, vex not
thy self with tears, praying and in treating for the oil of the tree of mercy, that thou
maest anoint thy father, Adam, for the pain of his body. For thou wilt not be able to receive
it's save in the last days.
in times, save when five thousand and five hundred years are accomplished. Then shall the
most beloved Son of God come upon the earth to raise up the body of Adam and the bodies
of the dead, and he shall come and be baptized in Jordan. And when he has come forth of
the water of Jordan, then shall he anoint with the oil of mercy all that believe on him,
and that oil of mercy shall be unto all generations of them that shall be born of water and of
the Holy Spirit unto life eternal.
Then shall the most beloved Son of God, even Christ Jesus, come down upon the earth, and
shall bring in our Father Adam into paradise unto the tree of mercy.
And when they heard all these things of Seth, all the patriarchs and prophets rejoiced
with a great rejoicing.
And while all the saints were rejoicing, behold, Satan, the prince and chief of death,
and to hell. Make thyself ready to receive Jesus who boasted them
self that he is the Son of God, whereas he is a man that fear death and saith, my soul
is sorrowful even unto death. And he hath been much mine enemy doing me great hurt, and
many that I had made blind, lame, dumb, leprous and possessed, he hath healed with a word, and
some whom I have brought unto thee dead, them hath he taken away from thee.
answered and said unto Satan the Prince. Who is he that is so mighty? If he be a
man that fear death. For all the mighty ones of the earth are held in
subjection by my power, even they whom thou hast brought me subdued by thy power.
If then thou art mighty, what manner of man is this Jesus, who though he feared death
resisteth thy power? If he be so mighty in his manhood, verily I say unto thee, he
is all mighty in his Godhead, and no man can withstand his power. And when he sayeth
that he feared death he wouldn't snare the
and woe shall be unto thee for ever lasting ages."
But Satan the Prince of Tardorus said,
"'Why doubt us thou, and furious to receive this Jesus,
which is thine adversary, and mine.
For I tempted him, and have stirred up mine
ancient people of the Jews with envy and wrath against him.
I have sharpened a spear to thrust him through gall
and vinegar have I mingle to give him to drink,
and I have prepared a cross to crucify him and nails to pierce him
and his death is night hands.
that I may bring him unto thee to be subject unto thee and me."
Hell answered and said,
Thou hast told me that it is he that hath taken away dead men from me,
for there be many which while they lived on the earth have taken dead men from me,
yet not by their own power but by prayer to God,
and their almighty God hath taken them from me.
Who is this Jesus which by his own word without prayer hath drawn dead men from me?
For chance it is he which by the word of his
command did restore to life Lazarus, which was four days dead and stank and was corrupt,
whom I held here dead."
Satan the Prince of Death answered and said,
"...It is that same Jesus."
When hell heard that, he said unto him,
"...I adjure thee by thy strength and my own that thou bring him not unto me."
For at that time I, when I heard the command of his word, did quake and was overwhelmed
with fear and all my ministries with me were troubled.
Neither could we keep Lazarus, but he, like an eagle, shaking himself, leaped forth with
all agility and swiftness and departed from us, and the earth also which held the dead
body of Lazarus straightway gave him up alive.
Therefore, now I know that that man which was able to do these things is a God strong
and command and mighty in manhood, and that he is the Savior of mankind.
And if thou bring him unto me, he will set free all that-
hear shut up in the hard prison, and bound in the chains of their sins that cannot be broken,
and will bring them unto the life of his Godhead forever.
And as Satan the Prince and Hell spoke this together, suddenly there came a voice as a thunder,
and a spiritual cry, remove, O Prince, as your gates and be lift up, ye everlasting doers
and the king of glory shall come in.
And hell heard that he said unto Satan the Prince.
Depart from me and go out of mine abode, if thou be a mighty man of war, fight thou against the King of glory.
But what has thou to do with him?
And hell cast Satan forth out of his dwelling.
Then said hell into his wicked ministers,
Shut ye the hard gates of brass, and put on them the bars of iron and withstand stoutly,
Lest we that hold captivity be taken captive.
But when all the multitudes of the scenes hurt it, they sp-
with a voice of rebuking unto hell. Open thy gates that the King of glory may come in."
And David cried out, saying,
"...Did I not when I was alive upon earth foretell unto you, let them give thanks unto the Lord,
even as mercies and as wonders unto the children of men who have broken the gates of brass,
and smitten the bars of iron and sunder, he hath taken them out of the way of their nicotine."
And thereafter in like manner Isaiah said,
Did not I when I was alive upon earth for tellin' to you?
you, the dead shall arise, and they that are in the tomb shall rise again, and they that
are in the earth shall rejoice for the dew which come up of the Lord is their healing.
And again I said, oh death, where is thy sting? Oh hell, where is thy victory?"
When they heard that of Isaiah, all the saints said unto hell, open thy gates, now shall
to thou be overcome, and weak, and without strength.
And there came a great voice as a thunder saying.
Remove, O princes, your gates and be, lift up ye doors of hell, and the king of glory shall come in."
And when hell saw that they so cried out twice, he said, as if he knew it not,
who is the king of glory? And David answered hell and said,
of the words of this cry, do I know, for by his spirit I prophesied the same,
and now I say unto thee that which I said before, the Lord strong and mighty, the Lord mighty
in battle, he is the king of glory.
The Lord looked down from heaven that he might hear the groanings of them that are in fetters
and deliver the children of them that have been slain, and now O thou most foul and stinking
hell, open thy gates that the king of glory may come in.
And as David spake thus unto hell, the Lord of Majesty appeared in the form of a man,
and lightened the eternal darkness, and break the bonds that could not be loosed, and the
sucker of his everlasting might.
visited us that sat in the deep darkness of our transgressions, and in the shadow of death of our sins.
When hell and death and their wicked ministers saw that, they were stricken with fear.
They end their cruel officers at the sight of the brightness of so great light in their own realm,
seeing Christ of a sudden in their abode, and they cried out saying,
cried out saying, we are overcome by the who art thou that art sent by the Lord for
confusion. Who art thou that without all damage of corruption, and with the signs that
thy majesty and blemished dust in wrath condemn our power? Who art thou that art so great
and so small, both humble and exalted, both soldier and commander, a marvelous warrior
in the shape of a bonsman, and a king of glory dead and living whom the cross bear slain
upon it? Thou that ditz lie dead in the sepulcher has come down unto us, living!
And at thy death all creation quaked, and all the stars were shaken, and thou has become
free among the dead, and just route our legions.
Who art thou that set us free, the prisoners that are held bound by sin and restore us
them into their former liberty?
Who art thou that set us thy divine and bright light upon them, that were blinded with
the darkness of their sins?
After the same manner, all the legions of devils were stricken with light fear, and cried out
out.
together in the terror of their confusion, saying,
Whence art thou, Jesus, a man so mighty and bright in majesty so excellent without spot and clean from sin.
For that world of earth which hath been always subject unto us until now and did pay tribute to our prophet,
hath never sent unto us a dead man like thee, nor ever dispatched such a gift unto hell.
Who then art thou that so fearlessly interest our borders and not only fear us not?
our torment, but besides, it says to bear away all men out of our bonds, per adventure
thou art that Jesus, of whom Satan our prince said that by thy death of the cross, thou
shouldst receive the dominion of the whole world.
Then did the king of glory in his majesty trample upon death and laid hold on Satan the prince
and delivered him unto the power of hell, and drew Adam to him.
to his own brightness.
Then hell-receiving Satan the Prince with soar reproached set unto him.
O Prince of perdition and chief of destruction bails above, the scorn of the angels and
spitting of the righteous, why wouldst thou do this?
Thou its crucifier, the king of glory, and at his decease, it's promise us great spoils
of his death, like a fool thou newest not without ditz.
to be hold now this Jesus puteth to flight by the brightness of His majesty.
be all the darkness of death, and at the broken the strong depths of the prisons, and let
out the prisoners, and loose them that were bound.
And all that were sighing in our torments, do rejoice against us, and at their prayers
our dominions are vanquished, and our realms conquered, and now no nation of men fear
us anymore.
And besides this, the dead which were never want to be proud triumph over us, and the captives
which never could be joyful do threaten us.
Oh, print
Satan, father of all the wicked and ungodly and renegades, wherefore would thou do this?
They that from the beginning until now have dispared of life and salvation.
Now is none of their wanted roarings heard, neither does any groan from them sound in our
ears, nor is there any sign of tears upon the face of any of them.
O Prince Satan, holder of the keys of hell, those thy riches which thou hast gained by the
tree of transgression and the losing of paradise now has lost by the tree of the
cross, and all thy gladness hath perished.
When thou dost hang up Christ Jesus the King of glory thou wroughtest against thyself and
against me.
Henceforth thou shalt know what eternal torment and infinite pains thou art to suffer in my
keeping forever.
O Prince Satan, author of death, and head of all pride thou audest first to have sought
out matter of evil in this Jesus.
therefore didst thou adventure without cause to crucify him unto
justly, against whom thou foundest no blame, and to bring into our realm the innocent and
righteous one, and to lose the guilty and the ungodly and unrighteous of the whole world.
And when hell had spoken thus unto Satan the Prince, then said the King of glory unto
hell. Satan the Prince shall be in thy power unto all ages in the stead of Adam and his
children, even those that are my righteous ones. And the Lord stretching forth...
his hand said,
of the Lord and treated him with tears and beceachings and said with a loud voice,
I will magnify the old Lord for thou hast set me up and not made my foes to triumph over me.
O Lord my God, I cried unto thee and thou hast healed me.
Lord thou hast brought my soul out of hell, thou hast delivered me from them that go down to the pit.
Sing praises unto the Lord all ye saints of his, and give thanks unto him for the remembrance of his
holiness, for there is wrath and is
indignation and life is in his good
pleasure.
And in like manner, all the saints of God mealed and cast themselves at the feet of the Lord,
saying with one accord,
Thou art come, O Redeemer of the world,
That which Thou disfortal by the law and by thy prophets thou hast accomplished indeed,
Thou hast redeems the living by thy cross,
And by the death of the cross thou hast come down unto us
That Thou mightest save us out of hell and death through thy majesty.
O Lord, like us thou has set the name of thy glory
in the heavens and set up thy cross for a token of redemption upon the earth, so Lord
set thou up the sign of the victory of thy cross in hell that death may have no more dominion.
And the Lord stretched forth his hand and made the sign of the cross over Adam and over
all his saints, and he took the right hand of Adam and went up out of hell, and all the
saints followed him. Then did Holy David cry aloud and say,
Sing unto the Lord a new song, for he has done marvelous things. His right hand has
brought salvation for him and his holy arm. The Lord has made known his saving health
before the face of all nations hath he revealed his righteousness.
And the whole multitude of the saints answered, saying,
"'Such honor have all his saints, Amen, Alleluia!''
And thereafter, Habakkuk the Prophet cried out and said,
The went just forth for the salvation of the
people to set free that chosen.
And all the saints answered saying,
Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord.
God is the Lord and it showed us light.
Amen, Alleluia.
Likewise after that, the prophet Micah also cried saying,
What God is like the O Lord taking away a
niquity and removing sins.
And now thou withholdest thy wrath for a testimony
that thou art merciful of free will.
And thou dost turn away and have mercy in us.
Now forgive us all-
all our niceties and has sunk all our sins in the depths of the sea, as thus swears unto
our fathers in the days of old.
And all the saints answered saying,
This is our God forever and ever, he shall be our guide,
World without end, Amen, Alleluia.
And so speak all the prophets, making mention of holy words out of their praises,
And all the saints follow the Lord,
Crying, Amen, Alleluia.
the Lord holding the hand of Adam delivered him unto
Michael the Archangel, and all the saints followed Michael the Archangel, and he brought them
all into the glory and beauty of Paradise.
And there met with them two men, ancients of days, and when they were asked of the saints,
who are ye that have not yet been dead in hell with us, and are set in Paradise in the
body?
Then one of them answering said, I am Inak, which was translated hither by the word of the
and this
that is with me is Elias the Tishbite, which was taken up in a chariot of fire.
And up to this day we have not tasted death, but we are received under the coming of Antichrist
to find against him, with signs and wonders of God, and to be slain of him in Jerusalem,
and after three days and a half, to be taken up again alive on the clouds.
And as Inak in Elias spake thus with the saints, behold, there came another man, a
habit, bearing upon his shoulders the sign of the cross, whom when they beheld all the
saints said unto him, who art thou? For thine appearance is as of a robber, and wherefor
is it that thou bearest a sign upon thy shoulders?" And he answered them and said,
he have rightly said, for I was a robber, doing all manner of evil upon the earth. And
the Jews crucified me with Jesus, and I beheld the wonders in the creation which came to
pass through the cross of Jesus when he was crucified.
And I believed that he was the maker of all creatures and the Almighty King.
And I besought him, saying, Remember me, Lord, when thou comest into the kingdom.
And forthwith, he received my prayer and said unto me, Verily, I say unto thee, This day
shall thou be with me in paradise.
And he gave me the sign of the cross, saying, Bear this, and go unto paradise.
the angel that keepeth parada
suffer thee not to enter in, show him the sign of the cross, and thou shalt say unto him,
Jesus Christ, the Son of God, who now is crucified, hath sent me. And when I had so done,
I spake all these things unto the angel that keepeth paradise. And when he heard this of me,
forthwith, he opened the door and brought me in and set me at the right hand of paradise, saying,
lo now Terry a little and Adam the father of all mankind will enter in with all his children
our holy and righteous. After the triumph and glory of the ascending up of Christ the Lord
that is crucified. When they heard all these words of the robber, all the holy patriarchs
and prophets said with one voice, Blessed be the Lord Almighty, the Father of eternal good
things, the Father of mercies, thou that has given such grace unto thy sinners and has
brought them again into the beauty of paradise and into thy good pastures, for this is the
the most holy life of the Spirit.
Amen, amen.
These are the divine and holy mysteries, which we saw and heard, even I,
Kerenus, and Lefkius. But we were not suffered to relate further the rest of
the mysteries of God. According as Michael the Archangel strictly charged us
saying, ye shall go with your brethren unto Jerusalem and remain in prayer,
crying out and glorifying the resurrection of the Lord Jesus Christ, who had
raised you from the dead together with him. And ye shall not be speaking with
And
man but sit as dumb men until the hour come when the Lord Himself suffered you to declare
the mysteries of His Godhead.
But unto us, Michael the Archangel gave commandment that we should go over Jordan unto a place
rich and fertile, where are many which rose again together with us for a testimony of the
resurrection of Christ the Lord.
For three days only were allowed unto us who rose from the dead, to keep the Passover
of the Lord in Jerusalem.
with our kindred that are living for a testimony of the resurrection of Christ the Lord.
And we were baptized in the Holy River of Jordan and received white robes every one of us.
And after the three days, when we had kept the Passover of the Lord, all they were caught
up in the clouds which had risen again with us, and we were taken over Jordan, and were
no more seen of any man.
But unto us it was said that we should remain in the city of Arimathea and continue in
in prayer.
These be all things which the Lord bade us declare unto you.
Give praise and thanksgiving unto him, and repent that he may have mercy upon you, peace
be unto you from the same Lord Jesus Christ which is the Savior of us all.
Amen.
And when they had finished writing all things, in the several volumes of paper they arose,
and Kareness gave that which he had written into the hands of Anis and Caiaphas and Gamalio,
Likewise, the
Levchius gave that which he had written into the hands of Nicodemus and Joseph, and suddenly
they were transfigured and became white exceedingly and were no more seen.
But their writings were found to be the same, neither more nor less by one letter.
And when all the synagogue of the Jews heard all these marvelous sayings of Kareness and
left-kiss. They said one to another. Of a truth, all these
things were wrought by the Lord, and blessed be the Lord world without end on men. And
they went out all of them in great trouble of mind, smiting their breasts with fear and
trembling, and departed every man unto his own home. And all these things which were
spoken by the Jews in their synagogue did Joseph and Nicodemus forthwith declare unto
the governor. And Pilate himself wrote all the things that were done and said concerning
Jesus.
by the Jews and laid up all the words in the public books of his judgment hall.
Thanks for listening, everyone.
This has been a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
Christ has risen.
He truly is risen.